Guide to the Dorothy M. Horstmann Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Dorothy M. Horstmann papers
1927-2001
1946-1995
MS 1700
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
17.75
The papers include include correspondence, writings, research data, notes, memorabilia, and photographs, which document Dorothy Horstmann's years at the Yale School of Medicine as a bio-medical researcher and teacher. The papers highlight her accomplishments in understanding and controlling the transmission of poliomyelitis and rubella.
Horstmann, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Millicent), 1911-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dorothy M. Horstmann, 1995-1996; gift of Arthur Ebbert, Jr., 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Associated Materials
John Rodman Paul Papers (MS 1333), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series: I. General Files, 1927-1995. II. Writings, 1946-1994, n.d. III. Teaching, 1947-1983. IV. Research and Consultations, 1940-1990. V. Professional Meetings, 1951-1994. VI. Personal Papers, 1941-2001. VII. Photographs, 1940-1994.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy Horstmann Papers include correspondence, writings, research data, notes, memorabilia, and photographs, which document Dorothy Horstmann's years at the Yale School of Medicine as a bio-medical researcher and teacher. The papers highlight her accomplishments in the epidemiology and conquest of poliomyelitis and rubella.
Horstmann's work as a virologist studying polio and rubella is amply documented in her writings and in extensive research data. The papers also include notes and reports from her research trips to Russia, Poland, Czechoslovakia, China, and Korea. While the papers contain a scant quantity of material from Horstmann's classroom teaching, they do reflect her role as a mentor to other scientists. The papers also chronicle Horstmann's involvement in professional organizations and her love of travel.
The collection includes a large quantity of materials related to John Rodman Paul, which document Horstmann's close working relationship with her mentor. This material consists of correspondence between Paul and Horstmann and with others concerning their joint projects. Evidence of her collaboration on Paul's publications is apparent in the papers, especially on her work to ensure the publication of Paul's History of Poliomyelitis. Other Paul materials in this collection include files on the preparation of a 1961 festschrift in Paul's honor and letters of condolence at his death.
Noticeably missing from the papers are materials about Horstmann's childhood or early career, and though Horstmann's appointment to an endowed chair at the university was a first, her papers contain little personal reflection on the challenges of being a woman scientist.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Millicent Horstmann was internationally known for her significant contributions to the understanding and control of poliomyelitis and congenital rubella. The many tributes and honors accorded her make clear how highly she was regarded as a researcher, clinician, teacher and friend.
Horstmann was born in Spokane, Washington, on July 2, 1911. After earning both her bachelors degree (1936) and her M.D. (1940) from the University of California, San Francisco and completing residencies at San Francisco County Hospital and at Vanderbilt University Hospital, she came to Yale University in 1942 as a post doctoral Commonwealth Fund fellow in the Section of Preventive Medicine of the School of Medicine. Here John Rodman Paul, director of the Yale Poliomyelitis Study Unit, stimulated her interest in the epidemiology and pathogenesis of viral infections. In 1944, she was appointed instructor in the Section of Preventive Medicine. She spent the year 1944/1945 as an instructor in the Department of Medicine at the University of California, San Francisco and 1947/1948 as a National Institutes of Health Fellow at the Institute of Medical Research in London. Otherwise, she served the entire remainder of her career as a faculty member at Yale. She became an assistant professor in 1948 and attained the rank of associate professorship in 1952. In 1961, she became the first woman to be appointed professor at the Yale School of Medicine. In 1969, when she became the John Rodman Paul Professor of Epidemiology and Public Health, she was the first woman ever to hold an endowed chair at the university. President Kingman Brewster appointed her to the Committee on the Status of Academic and Professional Women at Yale in 1970.
Horstmann's early research focused on the pathogenesis of the poliomyelitis virus. In 1946 she discovered that the virus is present in human blood during the incubation period of the infection but disappears later, when the neurologic symptoms begin. This research breakthrough implied that if serum antibodies could be induced by vaccination, the virus in the blood could be neutralized and thus prevent the virus from affecting the central nervous system. Demonstrated through carefully conceived experimental studies in monkeys and epidemiologically based human observations, this discovery became the basis for an efficacious vaccine against polio.
From 1955 to 1961, the Yale Poliomyelitis Unit evaluated immunization against poliomyelitis with live, attenuated vaccine, the Sabin vaccine. It carried out trials of both the Sabin and the Salk vaccines in New Haven, Guadalupe village in Arizona, Costa Rica, and also in Middletown and Southbury, Connecticut. Horstmann also evaluated the oral polio vaccine program in Russia, Czechoslovakia and Poland for the World Health Organization. The resulting report helped develop acceptance of the Sabin vaccine in the United States. In the 1960s and 1970s, Horstmann also did research on the clinical epidemiology of the rubella virus. Her work played a significant role in assuring the safety and effectiveness of rubella vaccine.
When John Rodman Paul died in 1971, leaving unfinished his History of Poliomyelitis, Horstmann took up the task of seeing this work through to publication and of producing a festschrift in his memory. In recognition of her scholarly contributions, Horstmann was elected to the National Academy of Science and the Royal Society of Medicine. In 1983, she chaired the Organizing Committee of the International Symposium on Poliomyelitis Control, sponsored by the National Institutes of Health Fogarty International Center. She served a term as president of the Infectious Diseases Society of America (1974/1975), and the Yale School of Medicine created an annual Dorothy M. Horstmann Lectureship as a continuing tribute. Horstmann died on January 18, 2001.
Poliomyelitis; Rubella; Virology; Women in medicine; Europe, Eastern -- Description and travel; Gear, James H. S. (James Henderson Sutherland), 1905-1994; Horstmann, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Millicent), 1911-; Madalengoitia, José; Von Magnus, Herdis; Miller, I. George; Morris, J. N. (Jeremy Noah); Paul, John R. (John Rodman), 1893-1971; Sabin, Albert B. (Albert Bruce), 1906-1993; Van Wagenen, Gertrude, 1893-; Yale University. Department of Epidemiology and Public Health; Yale University. School of Medicine
- General Files, 1927-1995, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists generally of correspondence with or about colleagues, institutions, publishers, periodicals, organizations, conferences, and committees. The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  The correspondence includes exchanges with or about several professional colleagues whom Horstmann also considered personal friends. Among these are I. George Miller, James Henderson, Sunderland Gear, Herdis von Magnus, José Madalengoitia, Jeremy Morris, and Gertrude Van Wagenen. Some of Horstmann's correspondence with Albert Sabin is filed in this series but their exchanges that concern the sharing results and specimens are filed in Series IV. There are almost no surviving personal family letters.
  Yale University files document women's issues at Yale, particularly in the 1970s. Files for the Yale University Committee on the Status of Women (also known as the Greene Committee), the Advisory Committee on the Education of Women, and the Yale Academic and Professional Women's forum contain discussions of contemporary concerns over women in research, the promotional ladder for women, maternity leave, child care, and discrimination.
  Horstmann's large number of John Rodman Paul files attests to the special working relationship between the two. The files detail their collaboration in research and publication. The Paul materials also include correspondence concerning publication of a festschrift in his honor and letters of sympathy at his death.
  Horstmann expressed some of her political convictions in letters to congressmen. These letters are filed in the section for United States Congress. Prominent among these are letters concerning the political situation in southern Africa.
  - A, 1954-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Pediatrics, 1961-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American College of Physicians, 1953-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Epidemiological Society, 1927-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Journal of Epidemiology, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Society for Clinical Investigation, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Society for Virology, 1981-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Society of Microbiology, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Andiman, Warren, 1972-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Andrewes, C. H., 1947-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Andrews, M. DeWayne, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Associates of the Cushing/Whitney Medical Library at Yale, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Association of American Physicians, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Atkins family, [1963?]-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B, 1960-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Banatvala, Jehangir E., 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Beeson, Paul B., 1963-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bishop, J. Michael, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brandsma, Janet, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brown, Nathaniel A, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Burrow, Gerald R., 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - C, 1946-1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - California. Department of Public Health, 1963-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cary, Alice S., 1973-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clinical Infectious Diseases, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Connecticut [State], 1958-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Connecticut Academy of Science and Engineering, 1981-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 28 - 29)
  - Connecticut Society for Medical Research, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Connecticut State Medical Society, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Contemporary OB/GYN, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - D, 1962-1994 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Dalldorf, Gilbert, 1958-1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Dave, Kanu, 1964-1986 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Davidson, Charles S., 1957-1982 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Delgado, Jose M. R., 1988-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Downey, T. Wayne, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - E, 1954-1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Edward, William O., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Enders, John F., 1955-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - European Society Against Virus Diseases, 1981-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Evans, Alfred S., 1951-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - F, 1953-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Fauci, Anthony S., 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Feinstein, Alvin R., 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Feldman. Harry A., 1963-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Forsgren, Marianne, 1972-1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - G, 1960-1994 (Box 3, Folder 49 - 50)
  - Gartshore, David and Pamela, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Gear, James Henderson Sutherland, 1947-1994 (Box 3, Folder 52 - 54)
  - Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1971-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - H, 1959-1983 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Hall, Carolyn Breese, 1968-1983 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Hart, James C., 1961-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Henderson, Ralph H., 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Hilleman, Maurice R., 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Hinman, Alan R., 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Horstmann family, 1945-1980 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Hostetter, Margaret K., 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Huessy, Hans R., 1988-1993 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Hummel, Cynthia, 1941-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - I, 1948-1990 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Infectious Diseases Society of America, 1968-1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 67 - 69)
  - Institute of Sera and Vaccines, 1984-1985, n. d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - International Association of Biological Standardization, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - International Epidemiological Association, 1971-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Isis, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Itescu, Silviu, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - J, 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Jackson, George Gee, 1966-1984 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Jensen, Hal B., 1984 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1979- 1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - K, 1953-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 79 - 80)
  - Kaplan, Bela, 1961-1987, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Kass, Edward H., 1971-1989 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Kennedy, Dermot H. and Catherine, 1976-1982 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Kilbourne, Edward D., 1984-1992 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Kinge, Birgitte, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Krause, Richard M., 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - L, 1945-1993 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Lasch, Eli E., 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Le Bouvier, George Louis, 1952-1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Lerner, A. Martin, 1966-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Liebhaber, Harvey, 1965-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Lucille P. Markey Charitable Trust, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - M, 1946-1995, undated (Box 5, Folder 93 - 94)
  - MacLean, Paul D., 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Madalengoitia, José, 1966-1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 96 - 97)
  - Magnus, Herdis von, 1946-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 98 - 102)
  - Manuscript Newsletter, 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - McAllister, Robert M., 1971-1984 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - McCollum, Robert W., 1966-1986 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Meakins, J. C., 1953-1959 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Medical Economics Books, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Medicine, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Meegan, James H., 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Melnick, Joseph and Sarah, 1955-1992 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Merck Manual, 1972-1989 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Miller, David G., 1964-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Miller, I. George, Jr.
    - General, 1963-1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 113 - 115)
    - Nominations [listed chronologically]
      - American Society for Clinical Investigation, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 116)
      - Macy Foundation Faculty Scholar Award Program, 1976, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
      - Squibb Award, 1981-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 118)
      - Lounsbery Award, 1982-1985 (Box 6, Folder 119)
      - National Academy of Sciences, 1984-1991, undated (Box 6, Folder 120)
      - Association of American Physicians, 1986-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 121)
      - Selman A. Waksman Award in Microbiology, 1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Miller, Louise T., 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Morio, Shinsuke, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Morris, Jeremy N., 1960-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 125 - 126)
  - Mullally, Daniel I., 1966 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - N, 1965-1991 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Nahmias, André J., 1968-1978 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - National Academy of Sciences
    - General, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - Committee on Human Rights, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 1986-1995 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - National Foundation for Infectious Diseases, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - National Institutes of Health
    - General, 1962-1981, undated (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - Advisory Committee to the Director, 1987, undated (Box 7, Folder 135)
    - National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, 1979-1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 136 - 138)
  - National Research Council
    - General, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 139)
    - Commission on Human Resources, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - National Science Foundation [proposal], 1975 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - New Haven, 1964-1982 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - New York Academy of Medicine, 1953-1988 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Niederman, James Corson, 1962-1993 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Niederman family, 1981-1990 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Nimmannitya, Suchitra, 1965-1993 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - O, 1950-1990 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - P, 1944-1987 (Box 7, Folder 148 - 149)
  - Pagano, Joseph S., 1969-1980 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Pajot, Thérèse G., 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Paul, John Rodman
    - Biographies and obituaries, 1959-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 152)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 153 - 156)
    - Letters informing correspondents of John Rodman Paul's death, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 157)
    - Letters of condolence, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 158)
    - Posthumous letters to which Horstmann responded, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 159)
    - Writings
      - An Account of the American Epidemiological Society, 1956-1994, undated (Box 8, Folder 160)
      - Infections Induced by Oral Administration of Attenuated Poliovirus to Persons Possessing Homotypic Antibody [with Horstmann et al], 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 161)
      - Poliomyelitis in 1957 [Yale Reports, radio broadcast] (Box 8, Folder 162)
      - Knowledge of Virus Diseases [St. Raphael's meeting], 1961 (Box 8, Folder 163)
      - History of Poliomyelitis [collaboration with Horstmann]
        - Correspondence, 1968-1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 164 - 166)
        - Reviews, 1971-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 167)
      - "A Trip to Japan in 1946", [1970?] (Box 9, Folder 168)
      - "Moments in Virology", 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 169)
      - Serological Epidemiology, edited with Colin White, 1970-1971, undated (Box 9, Folder 170)
      - "Rubella" by D. M. Horstmann, Chapter 9, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 171)
      - "Influenza and World War I. The A.E.F. Puts to Sea", 1971 (Box 9, Folder 172)
      - Two Early North American Archaeologists of the Southwest, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 173)
      - Thomas Francis, Jr. in Biographical Memoirs, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 174)
      - "Global Methods of Virus Disease Surveillance by Laboratory Methods", undated (Box 9, Folder 175)
      - "A Half-Century of Academic Preventive Medicine" [notes], undated (Box 9, Folder 176)
      - Various short pieces, undated (Box 9, Folder 177)
  - Paul, Oglesby, 1966-1980 (Box 9, Folder 178)
  - Paul family
    - Correspondence, 1966-1974, undated (Box 9, Folder 179)
    - "Notes Taken On a Tour Thro' France, Italy and Switzerland in the Spring and Summer of 1824" [Title page shows "by Jno Rodman Paul"] (Box 9, Folder 180)
  - Payne, Anthony M.-M., 1959-1967 (Box 9, Folder 181)
  - Pearson, Howard A., 1971-1982 (Box 9, Folder 182)
  - Pediatrics, Journal of the American Academy of Pediatrics, 1969-1976 (Box 9, Folder 183)
  - Pengelly, C. D. R., 1973-1978 (Box 9, Folder 184)
  - Philadelphia Variety Club, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 185)
  - Phillips, Charles Alan, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 186)
  - Plotkin, Stanley A., 1970-1987 (Box 9, Folder 187)
  - Q, 1974-1994 (Box 9, Folder 188)
  - R, 1946-1994, undated (Box 9, Folder 189 - 190)
  - Randolph, Martin F., 1968-1988 (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - Rapp, Fred, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 192)
  - Reviews of Infectious Diseases, 1982-1991 (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Robbins, Frederick C., 1988-1995 (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Robert, Marie F., 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - Robinson, James E., 1971-1985 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Rooney, Elizabeth, 1962-1966, undated (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Rosenberg, Leon E., 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - Rossier, E., 1975-1979 (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - Royal Society of Medicine, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 200)
  - Ruddle, Nancy H., 1976-1992 (Box 10, Folder 201)
  - Russell, W. Ritchie, 1947-1963 (Box 10, Folder 202)
  - S, 1946-1992, undated (Box 10, Folder 203 - 204)
  - Sabin, Albert B., 1952-1996, undated (Box 10, Folder 205 - 207)
  - Schleuderberg, Ann and Carl Jeffrey, 1976-1981, undated (Box 10, Folder 208)
  - Schmid, Rudy, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 209)
  - Shaw, Edward B., 1976-1979 (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Simmons, Dwayne, 1953-1991, undated (Box 10, Folder 211)
  - Singer, Maxine F., 1986-1991 (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - Smith, Leon J., 1981-1994 (Box 10, Folder 213)
  - Smith, Martin, 1979-1983 (Box 10, Folder 214)
  - Sociedad Uruguaya de Patalogia Clinica, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 215)
  - Sprinz, Helmuth, 1950-1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Stolwijk, Jan A. J., 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 217)
  - Stone, William, 1953-1965 (Box 10, Folder 218)
  - Subramanyan, T. P., 1981, undated (Box 10, Folder 219)
  - Summers, William C., 1976-1985 (Box 10, Folder 220)
  - Swanson-Kamen, Virginia, 1962-1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 221)
  - T, 1954-1992, undated (Box 10, Folder 222)
  - Tauve, Robert Victor, 1974-1982, undated (Box 11, Folder 223)
  - Taylor, Richard Moreland, 1961-1974, undated (Box 11, Folder 224)
  - Thisyakorn, Usa, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 225)
  - Thomas, Lewis, 1966-1990, undated (Box 11, Folder 226)
  - Tyrell, David A. J., 1989 (Box 11, Folder 227)
  - U, 1967-1985 (Box 11, Folder 228)
  - Union of Concerned Scientists, 1985-1992 (Box 11, Folder 229)
  - United States Congress
    - General, 1979-1991 (Box 11, Folder 230)
    - National Institutes of Health, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 231)
    - South Africa, 1985-1988 (Box 11, Folder 232)
    - TIAA-CREF Tax Reform, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 233)
    - Zimbabwe-Rhodesia, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 234)
  - United States. Surgeon General. Advisory Committee on Poliomyelitis Control, 1960-1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 235 - 236)
  - United States-Israel Binational Science Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 237)
  - University of California., San Francisco. Alumnus of the Year Award, 1989-1990, undated (Box 11, Folder 238)
  - University of Washington, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 239)
  - V, 1961-1993 (Box 11, Folder 240)
  - Van Wagenen, Gertrude, 1976-1993 (Box 11, Folder 241 - 242)
  - Vanderbilt University, 1984-1994, undated (Box 11, Folder 243)
  - Viseltear, Arthur J., 1980-1991 (Box 11, Folder 244)
  - Vonka, Vladimir, 1963-1983 (Box 11, Folder 245)
  - Voroshilova, Marina K., 1956-1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 246)
  - W, 1961-1994, undated (Box 11, Folder 247 - 248)
  - Walder, Raul, 1967-1970 (Box 11, Folder 249)
  - Wardale, Elizabeth, 1949-1956, undated (Box 11, Folder 250)
  - Wehrle, Pul F., 1964-1978 (Box 11, Folder 251)
  - Weinbren, Paul and Barbara, 1968-1977 (Box 11, Folder 252)
  - Weiser, Barbara, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 253)
  - Weller, Thomas H., 1977-1984 (Box 12, Folder 254)
  - Wessel, Morris A., 1969-1980 (Box 12, Folder 255)
  - White, Colin, 1963-1978 (Box 12, Folder 256)
  - Wilson, Daniel J. [includes interview with D. M. Horstmann], 1990-1994 (Box 12, Folder 257)
  - Wimmer, Eckard, 1983-1992 (Box 12, Folder 258)
  - Woodward, Theodore E., 1964-1990, undated (Box 12, Folder 259)
  - World Health Organization
    - Consultations: Russia, Czechoslovakia, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Folder 260)
    - Pan American Health Organization, 1968-1994, undated (Box 12, Folder 261 - 263)
    - Pan American Sanitary Bureau, 1955-1958, undated (Box 12, Folder 264)
  - Wyatt, H. Vivian, 1971-1980 (Box 12, Folder 265)
  - Y, 1959, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 266)
  - Yale Club of New York City, 1973-1985 (Box 12, Folder 267)
  - Yale-in-China